<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints gain by death, and their assurance thereof a sermon preached at the funerall of that worthy patriot Richard More, esquire, late one of the burgesses in this present Convention of Parliament for the town of Bishops-Castle in the countie of Salop / by Humphrey Hardwick ...</title>
            <author>Hardwick, Humphrey, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45539</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R279</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13649681</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13649681</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100971</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45539)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100971)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 789:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints gain by death, and their assurance thereof a sermon preached at the funerall of that worthy patriot Richard More, esquire, late one of the burgesses in this present Convention of Parliament for the town of Bishops-Castle in the countie of Salop / by Humphrey Hardwick ...</title>
                  <author>Hardwick, Humphrey, b. 1601 or 2.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.L. for Philemon Stephens ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Matthevv Clarke.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>More, Richard, d. 1643.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, V, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:100971:1"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Feb. 26. 1643.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>THis learned, pithy, and pertinent Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, claims of it ſelf more then a bare <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primatur,</hi> but the Author will not think much, if it be ſaid, <hi>Materia ſuperabat opus,</hi> ſuch was the Learning, language, exemplary piety, and happy pains in promoting the Goſpel of the worthily much honoured Gentleman, whoſe Funerals it ſolemnized, together with his conſtant faithfulnes and uſefulneſſe to his Countrey and Religion, in deſpight of all dangers, loſſes, ſufferings, that he deſerves a juſt Volume to tranſmit the beams of ſuch a light to poſterity, wherein I dare ſay the higheſt wit and love met in one, might ſooner grow bankrupt, then prodigall.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Charles Herle.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100971:1"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS GAIN BY DEATH, And their Aſſurance thereof.</p>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE Funerall of that worthy Patriot <hi>Richard More,</hi> Eſquire, late one of the Burgeſſes in this preſent Convention of Parliament for the Town of Biſhops-Caſtle in the Countie of <hi>Salop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Humphrey Hardwick,</hi> Chaplain to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> L General, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>The Text. 2 COR. 5.1.</bibl>
               <p>For we know, that if our earthly houſe of this tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hand, eternall in the heavens.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens,</hi> at the ſign of the Gilded Lion in Pauls Church-yard. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100971:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100971:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MVCH AND WORTHILY HONOVRED Sir ROBERT HARLEY, Knight of the Honourable Order of the Bath, and Knight of the Honorable Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons for the County of <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſoul-weaning Funerall Sermon, preached by my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend brother, at the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of my much honoured Vncle, <hi>Richard More</hi> Eſquire, being through the importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſome brought from him unto me to be put in Print, and recommended to whom I ſhuld think fit: I knew not who could better make atteſtation to this indefatigable Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors worth then your ſelf, his boſome friend.</p>
            <p>What teſtimonie is here given him, either by my faithfull brother, or by me, is but an Epitome of yours, and his Countreyes lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:100971:3"/> knowledge of him. He ſpent his laſt breath in proſecuting and promoting that Scripture-Church-Reformation, whereunto his parents had been zealous Witneſſes: who were not more carefull of his education in religion, and learning, then he was apt to take it. In ſo much, that at ten yeers of age he was able to read the Old Teſtament in the originall. Though the death of his father in his youth diverted him from going to the Vniverſitie: yet he grew ſo active for the publike, that it is hard to tell, whether he did more ſervice to his Countrey before, or after he was in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of the peace. I ſhould ſorrow as a man without hope of repair of his Countreys loſſe, but that he hath left a ſon, as fit to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed him in his place, as in his eſtate. In diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult buſineſſes, for his Countrey, he was not wont to ſtrain courteſy, to follow others: but was willing to lead the way, and break the Ice. He was a Sanctuary to conſcientious men in their perſecutions. I could name ſome, who falling into <hi>limbum patrum,</hi> I mean the courts of Tyrannizing Prelates, who found him ready by his travails, friends, counſell, purſe, to helpe them out. He would loſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friend he had to ſtand for the right of his
<pb facs="tcp:100971:3"/> pooreſt neighbour. He was a friend, ſo throughly cordiall, that in all his undertakings for any, on any occaſion, with <hi>Boaz,</hi> he could not reſt, till he had effected it. He was a countenancer, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holder and frequenter of Lectures &amp; Lecturers. He hated vice in all, but eſpecially in Miniſters, whom yet he had rather reclaim then ruine; and he was wont to let them know, that he ſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their parts, as he abhorred their exorbitancies. As Chriſt deſcended to do his Fathers will, ſo he was willing to ſtoop to any place below himſelf to do his neighborhood ſervice. He was no <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, no ſelf-putting-forth man, he ſought rather to be, then ſeem ſtrict. He much honoured the Lords day and his Miniſters; his opinion was to his death, there was due to God a 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. part of our time, and a 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. part of our eſtate. Some of his laſt words were, How are the Miniſters provided for? He lived much by faith, eſpecially in theſe ſad and exhauſting times: as appeares not onely by his deeds, his caſting into the publike treaſurie all his plate, &amp; all that he could make or get; but alſo, by ſuch as theſe his latter ſpeeches: Every man muſt riſe &amp; fall with the publike. We muſt give all for gone, and wait what God will do for it. And it makes no matter what becomes of me and mine, ſo it go well with the publike, as
<pb facs="tcp:100971:4"/> I am confident it will in a ſhort time. And when ſome told him it was like to go ill w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Shropſhire: He anſwered, Shropſhire wants faith, as well as other places. And when ſome of his family to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his end was ſpeaking ſolicitouſly to him: God (ſaid he) that feeds the Ravens, will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you to want. I do not love theſe diſtracting thoughts. Thus his faith wrought with his works to the laſt. And yet it no whit blunted his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry for the good of his family. A carefull father he was of his children, for whom (being four ſons and one daughter) he had provided plentifully in his life; and a tender husband over his dear and pious conſort, who had lived with him above 50. yeers, and had done him much good, and no hurt, all the days of his life, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he left by will, made three yeers before his death, 400. l. over &amp; above joynture; but the Lord hath given and the Lord hath taken away, and w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> of his, here, can now ſay his bread is his own? Such is the rapine of war. From which he is now freed, being abſent from his body, preſent with his Lord: to which marke you alſo are preſsing forward, as a Taper daily ſpending your ſelf, to light others. The Lord make you and your poſterity to fare the better for your publick faithfulneſſe: ſo prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips to ſerve you in the Lord, <hi>MATTHEVV CLARKE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100971:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE SAINTS GAIN BY DEATH: And his aſſurance thereof, Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted and applied.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2. COR. 5.1.</bibl>
                  <p>For we know that if our earthly houſe of this Tabernacle were diſſolved, we have a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternall in the heavens.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE yeeres of man are threeſcore and ten, (ſaid <hi>David</hi>) a great while compared to an houre; but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered with eternity, they ſeem ſcarce a minute. The ſwift re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution of all-eating time ſoon rowls up the thread of mans life: the day by houres, the moneth by dayes; the yeer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100971:5"/> by moneths, our age by yeers ſoon ſteps away. Our infancie is like yeſterdayes evening, we have ſlept and forgot it; Our youth, the morning paſt, our man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood the mid-day preſent, old age comes anone. He who hath paſt theſe ſtages, knowes beſt the truth of this. For time paſt is a certainty found to be nothing, time to come an uncertainty, ſeeming to bee much, time preſent is a fleeter; the Sun goes, and the Sand runs, quickly do we bring our ſeventy to an end, as a tale that is told. But alas who can promiſe himſelfe that number? not one of multitudes live thus long. How many waies do miſerie and death conſpire to fetch us off in the ſeverall ages of our life? Poor mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls, we are incident to a diſſolution every day. Hence ſome of the wiſer Heathen defining our life called it, <hi>Mortis imago,</hi> an image of death, <hi>acceſſus &amp; deceſſus,</hi> an entrance, and an <hi>exit.</hi> The Philoſophers iudgement was, <hi>optimum non naſci, proximum citò ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olert;</hi> but we Chriſtians are men of better hopes, and can make more comfortable deſcription of our pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage. We may call it the dawning of an eternall day, the Eave of a glorious Feſtivall; a way wherein we walke to bleſſedneſſe, and whether this be long or ſhort, the matter is not great; if we waite long, the tediouſneſſe of expectance will be recompenced with encreaſe of welcome: if we ſoon end the jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of this life, the leſſe will be our ſhare of miſery: whether thus, or thus long or ſhort, a good Chriſtian ſhould not care much: <hi>For we know if our earthly houſe of this tabernacle, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words ſtand in the book of God as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to confirme ſomething which went before.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100971:5"/> S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the precedent Chapter, is in a holy contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, as it were balancing his preſent afflictions with his future hopes. Thoſe he findes ſtinted, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, bordered with timely freedome and delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; but of the latter there is no end, his hopes are things bleſſed,<note place="margin">Chap. 4 8.</note> eternall, tending to his own ſpirituall advantage and the Churches Emolument. Whence he concludes that his affliction which was but <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> light &amp; for a moment did work an <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ver. 17. With abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon abundance.</note> exceeding eternall weight of glory. And leſt this affirmation might ſeem ſtrange, the Apoſtle doth demonſtrate how hee collects it, not from the things which are ſeen, being temporall; from which no ſuch weight of glory can ſpring, but from the things which are not ſeen, theſe are eternall, theſe make up the weight of the forementioned glory: to theſe S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> hath an eye, of theſe inviſibles he is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certained, <hi>For wee know, ſaith hee, that if our earthly houſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Text thus placed in the book of God tenders to our view a double proſpect, here is an houſe and a building to be ſeen. Now an houſe we know is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an habitation for man to abide or dwell in; the thing therefore which is Metaphorically ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is either theſe organized bodies which wee bear about, or elſe it muſt be underſtood of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall life or ſtate of being which we have in this world; by three <hi>Items</hi> charactered out unto us in my Text. Firſt, this houſe is deſcribed <hi>ab origine, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> it is from the earth, ſo ſaith the ſame Author, the firſt man is of the Earth, Earthie. No better me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall then the Potter uſeth to frame his pitchers of,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100971:6"/> to that the Apoſtle ſeems to allude, and intimates the brickle frailty of our preſent ſtate. Secondly, we have the houſe deſcribed, <hi>a ſtatu mutabili</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of a Tabernacle, a moveable kinde of habitation, every night almoſt it findes a new place. Here wee have no abiding City, wee continue not at one ſtay, <hi>nec utì, nec ubì, ſtatu</hi> nor <hi>gradu:</hi> We run the chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, paſſe from one condition to another, ſo mutable is our earthly houſe. Laſtly, it is pointed out <hi>ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritu,</hi> it is a houſe of a periſhing diſſolving frame, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this ſuppoſition is not ſo much to be underſtood <hi>de re periturâ,</hi> as <hi>de modo ſive tempore reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendi,</hi> it is paſt all paradventure, that this houſe of tabernacle will be diſſolved, but the manner how, the time when, may be ſuppoſed: the Apoſtle then gives all men leave to imagine that the preſent trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and afflictions which he then ſuſtained, the great and imminent dangers wherein hee was plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, might happily burſt the thread of his life, before his naturall courſe were run, or by ſome violent diſſolution. If thus or thus, it is but a haſtie injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pulling down of a houſe which would otherwiſe diſſolve it ſelf after a little more time, for it is but a <hi>periſht</hi> houſe.</p>
            <p>The latter proſpect in our view is a building, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an habitation of a more rare ſtately frame, by this we muſt underſtand, the ſtate of an holy ſoul departed, of a good Chriſtian in another world. This building is one of thoſe <hi>Manſions</hi> of which our Saviour ſpeakes of, <hi>Iohn</hi> 14. And in the Text we have it deſcribed, Firſt, from the builder and author, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of God. We attain to our earthly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100971:6"/> Tabernacle by an order eſtabliſhed of God in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; we have by means and ſecond cauſes, all the things of this life: but the building which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, is given immediately by God. <hi>Thou ſhalt bring me to glory,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. It is our Fathers will to give the Kingdom himſelfe: ſure it will make our future ſtate the more excellent, that we have it immediately from the bleſſed hand of God. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, this building is ſet forth in the quality of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> not made with hands, it is not of a viſible make, or frame, tooles and inſtruments were not imployed to compoſe it. <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> The pure eternall will of God framed this manſion according to his own coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, ſecret to us: A building removed far beyond the reach of mans capacity, which is, Thirdly, deſcribed in the Text, from the ſtability and perpetuity of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> eternall, not for dayes, and for moneths, for times and for ſeaſons, but for ever is this building framed. Laſtly, it ſets out the dignitie of place, this building is in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in heaven, that Empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Throne of the moſt High, where dwells bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for evermore. Thus wee have ſeen the houſe and building in the ſeverall paſſages of my Text.</p>
            <p>We may next conſider whoſe theſe are, to whom they doe belong: and remarkable it is, that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle doth expreſſe no ſpeciall intereſt in the former. He calles it a houſe of Tabernacle; the word <hi>this</hi> in Engliſh is more then is in the Originall. The houſe of Tabernacle is a common habitation, where all the ſons of <hi>Adam</hi> dwell alike: Gods Elect can claime no more intereſt in this then others; well then may the Apoſtle paſſe this without an <hi>Item</hi> of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100971:7"/> proprietie; whilſt he claimes the latter in a ſpeciall manner, ſaying, <hi>We have a building:</hi> by which he literally and immediately, points out his own inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and in his, intimates the right of all the Saints, like as in another place he ſaith, A crowne is laid up for me, and not for me onely, but for all that love his appearing. True and rightly beleeving Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have this honour, that the building not made with hands is onely theirs.</p>
            <p>The third conſiderable circumſtance in my Text is the order, &amp; here we may note, the firſt is that which is naturall, then that which is ſpirituall; the firſt is of the Earth, earthie, the ſecond in Heaven, heavenly; By the frail houſe we paſſe to the firme habitation, when the former is diſſolved, the latter takes place.</p>
            <p>The laſt thing I ſhall propound is the note Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty: in the firſt word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>We know:</hi> it was not a thing S. <hi>Paul</hi> much doubted, or had a meer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit or conjecture of, but a thing of which he was fully perſwaded. He knew of a certainty, that when his earthen Tabernacle was diſſolved, he ſhould be poſſeſſed of the Heavenly building: and what he ſpeakes for himſelfe, he intimates for the comfort of others, of all that are veſſels of honour, heirs of grace, called by the Word and ſanctified.</p>
            <p>Theſe the ſeverall paſſages conſiderable in the words I read, yeeld us three circumſtances of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doctrine.
<list>
                  <item>1 From the deſcription of our earthly Manſion, we may collect, that our eſtate in this life is fraile, tranſitory, periſhing.</item>
                  <item>2. From the excellency of the building, not made
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100971:7"/> with hands, we gather that the ſtate of a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in the world to come, is bleſſed and eternall in the heavens.</item>
                  <item>3. By the note of certainty we may conclude, that every converted heart, and carefull ſoul may and ought to be aſſured, that when his body ſhall be diſſolved, his ſoul ſhall have an happy dwelling with God in heaven.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe ſentences of holy doctrine are too plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubjects to be fully diſcourſed of in one Sermon: I will ſpeak in a word of the two former, and but briefly of the laſt.</p>
            <p>That our ſtate and condition in this life is fraile, tranſitory, periſhing, who can deny? Let old <hi>Iacob</hi> come in, and he will affirm, that few and evill are the dayes and yeers of his life: and, My dayes are ſwifter then a weavers ſhuttle: Oh remember that my life is wind, ſaid <hi>Iob:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 7.6, 7.</note> And again, is not man born to trouble as ſparks flie upward? The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is wont to compare our preſent ſtate with things moſt frail &amp; periſhing. Our life is as a flower, as ſmoke, a dew, a blaſt, a breath, a bubble, it is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, it is as nothing.</p>
            <p>I fetch arguments to confirm this from what we are; and what are the beſt things we can have?
<list>
                  <item>1. Conſider we have frail bodies, no better then a lump of earth, an handfull of wormes; at beſt, liable to a thouſand griefs, paines, aches, diſeaſes, diſtempers.</item>
                  <item>2. Have we not frail ſpirits alſo, ſubject to many troubles, doubts, feares, terrours, perplexities and amazes?</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:100971:8"/>
            <p>What is the union of theſe, being our naturall life, but a fading, periſhing, dying kind of being, ſtill ſpending it ſelf, and burning out its own candle? They have judged right, who have wrote, that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and mans life are convertible tearms: And when the Limners do picture ſorrow, they make it like a man. Thus from what we are we may ſee this truth.</p>
            <p>And what good things doth this life afford? riches, honours, pleaſures, and ſecular learning.</p>
            <p>As for riches,<note place="margin">Riches.</note> what are theſe but a finer kinde of earth, having an high price ſtamped on it? and if man could compaſſe all the treaſure under heaven, what a deal of diſcontenting gold would there be? too much to uſe, too little to content the greedy heart of man: <hi>Midas</hi>-like we would be glad to be rid of our firſt wiſh: Not all, but a part would man have, yet I trow it's the biggeſt part: <hi>Dives</hi> would have none ſo rich as he. <hi>Sed, quid juvat im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſum,</hi> what good will a great heap do us? was ever man happy in abundance? great riches is but matter of trouble, dangerous to the poſſeſſor, an ill maſter, a treacherous ſervant: There is a dying na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in them, they have wings and will be gone, and yeeld but little content while they ſtay; for he that loveth ſilver is not ſatisfied with it, this is va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and vexation of ſpirit.</p>
            <p>What are honours in this life,<note place="margin">Honours.</note> but ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed excellencies, which have no true being, accompanied with cares and cumber, the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject as well of envie as of eſteem? If we could go to the aſhes of dead <hi>Alexander,</hi> they'l tell us
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100971:8"/> what he found in his great preferments: ſurely they would acquaint us, that thoſe honours were not worth the labour, <hi>equitandì per Britannos &amp; curſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandi per Germanos, pati pruinam.</hi> It was a ſubtle trick of Satan when he tempted Chriſt with the offer of worldly honours, that he ſhewed onely the Kingdoms of the earth and the glory of them; never pointing out the cares, troubles, diſcontents which abounded in thoſe kingdoms, for then they would have been no provocation at all. The man in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> ſaid wiſely, that he who conſiders the troubles of a Crown well, would not gather it up in the ſtreet. The happineſſe of great places is more in that they are thought ſo, then that they are ſo. You that are our Senators do now throughoutly know what poor happineſſe it is to be inceſſantly troubled with a world of other mens buſineſſes, and have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle time to think on your ſelvs and your own affairs; and lo, that is the good of high places. I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare earthly honours to the plate at a Lottery, it is expoſed to open view, makes a great ſhew, and if a man do chance to light on a priſe, it is no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, only it is drummed out, and trumpeted abroad, to tell the world; and this is the glory of it: Even ſo, if ſome of thoſe many that venture hard for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours do ſpeed, it is no ſuch great matter, onely the buſineſſe is trumpeted out, told abroad, and the world hath ſome apprehenſion of it; but alas, the wiſeſt of mortals found this alſo to be vanitie; yea, a fleeting vanitie,<note place="margin">Gloria Crocodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</note> flying faſteſt from ſuch as purſue it moſt: How oft hath one day found a man in high honours and low diſgrace?</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:100971:9"/>
            <p>A third ſort of the beſt things of this life are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures;<note place="margin">Pleaſures.</note> now what froth? what chaffe? what no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things are theſe? I may ſever them into harmleſſe recreations, or ſinfull delights; the former, being the beſt of pleaſures, are a kind of fading vanities, which periſh in the uſe of them; there is but a meer ſhadow of content in them, which we apprehend to be before us; but alas, wee ſeldome overtake it. Caſt back your thoughts on our youthfull paſtimes, how did we prize our gains and hopes of winning but an handfull of Counters? no pleaſures in the world I think can ever ſo much take us as thoſe did; yet a few years with diſcretion do ſhew us what poor contentments they were: Manhood deems as meanly of the frolicks of our youth, age and riper judgement well knows all pleaſures to be a fleeting joy, which is gone as ſoon as had. As for ſinfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, Satan ſo tampers with our natures, as to make them ſeem great in expectation before they are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; but when they come to be poſſeſſed they vaniſh: What ſugared delights do beloved ſinnes promiſe? but alas, they ſtill ſhamefully deceive our expectation; the delight wings away, and the act leaves a guilt behind. How little is our life the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for our pleaſures?</p>
            <p>The laſt ornaments of our earthly tabernacles is humane or ſecular learning;<note place="margin">Learning. <hi>Litera tutiſſimae ſunt divitiae, quae nec eripi poſſunt nec gravant cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumferentem. Eraſm.</hi>
               </note> theſe I grant are of all the ſafeſt treaſures, they can neither be plundered, nor be they burthenſome to the bearer; but true it is, that no full content or perfection can be had in knowledge; fraile man but weake of brain, hath his veſſell too ſhallow to comprehend ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100971:9"/> Our ſtudy doth but learn us of our want, put us on to a further ſearch into letters, and render us ſtill leſſe ſatisfied. I gave my heart, ſaid <hi>Solomon,</hi> to know wiſdom, and I perceived that this alſo is vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit; for in much wiſdom is much grief, and he that increaſeth knowledge, increaſeth ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.17, 18.</p>
            <p>Lo thus, my brethren, we have taken a brief view of all the things which our earthly houſe of this ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle doth afford, and we have found as well by what we have, as what we are, that our ſtate and condition here is frail, tranſitory, periſhing: As evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent likewiſe will it appear, that the building not made with hands, the ſtate of a faithful ſoul after this life, is bleſſed and eternall.</p>
            <p>Witneſſe firſt the many titles of excellencie which in Gods book are given to it: The Apoſtle ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, calls it the riches, glory, and inheritance of Saints in light; ſo he ſtiles it by way of eminencie: Now riches doth there comprehend all things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, glory all things gracefull and delighting; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance ſignifieth perpetuity, everlaſtingneſſe. In other places it is called light, life, joy, bleſſedneſſe; all in abſtracts, to intimate the moſt tranſcendent perfections that can be. Yea, more, it is affirmed to be a kingdom, to be a Crown; to be a kingdom of glory, to be a crown of life, to be an eternall weight of glory, which paſſeth not away: The time would fail me to ſet forth the leaſt part of that high praiſe, thoſe ſweet and admirable teſtimonies which the holy Scriptures give of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. And in reaſon it may appear thus, if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100971:10"/> who provided this building, and at what rates it was purchaſed. Know we then, that as it was not of mans framing, ſo was it not of his providing; this was ſuch a building as eye had not ſeen, nor eare heard, nor could it enter into the heart of man, it was not in his power to turn his hand to making of any ſuch proviſion; none of them can by any means redeem his brother, or give God a ranſome; the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of the ſoul is pretious, man muſt let that alone for ever, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.7, 8. nor could the Angels reach this work, they fell and cannot help them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs; nor can their own fellow Angels ſteed them in this behalf, it was an infinit work to provide theſe manſions; none therefore but the bleſſed Sonne of God, who is coequall with the Father, could prepare this building, nor could he obtain it at any lower rate then his own precious blood, ſhed in a moſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious and curſed manner: and by this we may gueſſe at the worth of this building.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, conſider for whom it is provided: not for the world, Chriſt would not ſo much as pray for them; it was for his own, for thoſe who were his Fathers children, the elect of God, holy and beloved, the ſonnes and daughters of the King of glory. If men that are evill will provide fair buildings for their children, what buildings will our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his Son provide for his? Yet more, theſe Manſions were prepared for the beſt of Angels, thoſe incomparable ſpirits which remained pure as they came out of the hands of God. Chriſt provided the place we ſpeak of for their eternal habitation: which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100971:10"/> may ſufficiently prove the building not made with hands, to be bleſſed and glorious.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, call we to mind the chiefe end for which it ſerves, namely, to manifeſt therein the higheſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Gods revealed glory, and to participate the moſt tranſcendent meaſure of happineſſe to the chiefeſt creatures; therefore this building, that ſtate and condition muſt needs be bleſſed and eternall in the heavens.</p>
            <p>If I had time to ſtay on this point, I could further illuſtrate the glory of our future condition in the particulars of it: As 1. the taking again of the ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bleſſed hands of God who gave it. 2. The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of it with glorious endowments, poliſhing it for an heavenly eternall being. 3. The actuall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance of it into the Empyreall heaven that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. 4. The conjoyning or planting of it into the all-raviſhing ſocietie of Saints and Angels. 5. The uniting of it to our glorified Saviour as its head or husband. 6. The conferring on it fulneſſe of joy and infinite rivers of pleaſures. 7. The filling of it with the bleſſed viſion and fruition of Jehovahs face in glory. Take a glimpſe of theſe things in the ſight of our minds, and I ſhall need ſtay no longer in the confirmation of the point.</p>
            <p>Now the light of theſe holy truths reflected on our ſelves, doth wonderfully accuſe almoſt all men and women of folly and madneſſe, for our ſo much love, ſeeking, joying, delighting and contenting our ſelves in our earthly houſe of this tabernacle: how fooliſh and unwiſe are we to chuſe the worſer, baſer building, to be taken up wholly with the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100971:11"/> things before us, to place our heart and affections on things below, which are fraile, tranſitory, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing. Wee can blame <hi>Eſau</hi> for preferring a meſſe of pottage before his birth-right; <hi>Ahab</hi> for ſelling his ſoul to get a vineyard; the fool for building big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger barnes, and ſolacing his ſoul with goods laid up; but alas, we are many of us guilty of the ſame folly; we live taken up with a ſecure joy out of a vain ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of pleaſure in our preſent ſtate and the enjoyment of outward things; as if we had choſen them to be our chiefe portion, and this world to be our Heaven: Your conſciences can tel you that you are even more guiltie then I can ſpeak; you do and will love moſt the houſe of tabernacle, and will not be perſwaded to unglue your affection, and take off the eagerneſſe of your purſuit after the things that periſh. We have many warnings, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in theſe times, from heaven, from earth, from God, from man, by the loſſe of goods, friends, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, lands, fathers, children, husbands, all beſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to abate our love to the world, and the things of this world; yet pitie it is, few or none will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a due and dutifull conſideration of the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of theſe worldly things, or once in good earneſt endeavour to wean their hearts from theſe earthen Tabernacles.</p>
            <p>As faulty likewiſe and blame worthy are we for our ſupine negligence, our extream careleſneſſe, our want of love to, &amp; eſteem of the building not made with hands, the ſtate of a bleſſed ſoule after this life. Who hath ſuch high upriſing thoughts of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture condition as it deſerves? few there be that take
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100971:11"/> it into ſerious meditation at all; Moſt men ſeem to determine of their ſoules, (as the Jewes ſaid of Chriſt) Let God ſave them, if he will have them: We are bent to enjoy that which is preſent, and think little what ſhall become of our ſoules, when our fleſh ſhall ſinke into the grave. As therefore our too much care of this earthly Tabernacle, ſo our too little regard of the heavenly building, is a juſt ſhame and reproach unto us: now to make every ſoule truely ſenſible and mindefull of our great miſcariage in this buſineſſe, I will give you a Parable of a woman, which travelling with child brought forth a Twin, and both children being preſented to her, ſhe falles deepely and fondly in love with the one, but is careleſſe, diſreſpectfull of the other; this ſhe will nurſe her ſelf, but that is put forth; her love growes up with the childe ſhe kept her ſelfe, ſhe decks it fine, ſhe feedes it choicely; but at laſt, by overmuch pampering of it the childe ſurfets, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes mortally ſick, and when it was dying, ſhe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members her ſelf and ſends to looke after the other childe that was forth at nurſe, to the end ſhe might now cheriſh it: but when the meſſenger came, ſhe findes it dying and gaſping likewiſe, and examining the truth, ſhe underſtands that through the mothers careleſneſſe and neglect to looke after it the poore childe was ſtarved: thus was the fond partiall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to her great ſorrow and ſhame, deprived of both her hopefull babes. For reddition of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, you may pleaſe to take notice that every Chriſtian is this mother, the children are our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and our ſoule, our earthly and ſpirituall
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100971:12"/> building; the former of theſe it is, that men and women fall deeply and fondly in love with, whilſt indeed they are careleſſe and neglect the other, this they dreſſe and feed, nothing is too good or dear for it; but at the laſt, the bodie ſurfets, comes by ſome means or other to its death-bed, when there is litle or no hope of life, then men begin to remember the ſoul, and would think of ſom courſe to ſave it, the Miniſter he is ſent for in all haſte to look after it: but alas! he finds it in part dead, in part dying, and the very truth is, the owner through neglect and careleſneſſe hath ſtarved the Soul, and it is ready to goe to Hell, before the bodie is ready for the Grave; and thus the fooliſh fond Chriſtian, to his eternall ſorrow and ſhame, loſeth both his bodie and his ſoul: and may not this throughoutly check the extreame folly, and indiſcretion which the world is guiltie of?</p>
            <p>I ſhall then cloſe theſe two points with a word of admonition; ſince it is evident that the building, not made with hands, is ſo tranſcendently more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent then the earthen Tabernacle, let it be the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of our cares, and chiefeſt of our endeavours to lay up treaſure in heaven. Labour not ſo much for the food that periſheth, as for that which endureth for ever. Seek all wayes, uſe all meanes to be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed on with that houſe from above. And for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive or inducement to this, I will uſe onely one, not of mine own framing, but a ſhaft, as it were, out of the Lords Armorie. They are our Saviours own words. <hi>What ſhall it profit a man to win the whole world and loſe his own ſoul?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100971:12"/>
            <p>I come now to the laſt circumſtance of Doctrine; every converted heart and careful ſoul may and ought to be aſſured, that when his body ſhall be diſſolved, his ſoul ſhall have a dwelling with God in heaven. And firſt in teſtimony that there is a certaintie, I alledge, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1. <hi>There is no condemnation to thoſe that are in Chriſt Ieſus, who live not after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit.</hi> Lo here an expreſſe affirmation of the thing, and a manifeſt deſcription of the perſons.<note place="margin">Numerus certus non ſolum quoad numerum numerantem ut ſuggerant Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niani ſed quoad numerum nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum ut ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxi tenent.</note> In the 2. of <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. we have a like proof. The foundation of God ſtandeth ſure, having this ſeal, <hi>The Lord knoweth who are his;</hi> ſee, my brethren, it is not onely how many are elected, but who they are, who be the very individuall and numericall perſons. That regenerate men may and ought to gain aſſurance is likewiſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident by ſuch places as enjoyn us ſtrictly to examine our ſelves, whether we be in the faith or not, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5 to prove our ſelvs and our own work, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4. to make our calling and election ſure, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. Were not the precepts of this kinde ſtrange, if we could not, if we ought not be aſſured? Adde to this the many properties, qualities, ſignes, tokens ſet down in Scripture, to deſign and note out the Elect of God. Was not <hi>Iob</hi> certain, that his Redeemer lived? yet we find not, that he had any revelation or extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary warrant: But why do I inſtance one, ſince all the Worthies in Gods book did attain to a certaintie of faith,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heb. 11.39</note> and ſerve as a cloud of witneſſes to prove my truth?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Which I may yet further confirm by divers ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, the many cleer promiſes which the Lord made to the faithfull in his Book for their eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20, 21. Doth not every dutifull ſonne
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100971:13"/> aſſure himſelf of that portion which his good Father hath promiſed him? How much more may the heires of glory be aſſured of that our heavenly Father ſo plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully promiſed?</p>
            <p n="2">2 Our bleſſed Saviour hath fully purchaſed our ſalvation, and compleatly juſtified all his: for God was in Chriſt, reconciling the world to himſelf from the beginning; and may not we be aſſured of our inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſince the price is paid?</p>
            <p n="3">3 Chriſt doth continually pray for us at the right hand of God, ſaying, Father keep them, for they are thine, and thine are mine; and ſure it is, none ſhall take his ſheep out of his hand.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The Lord hath vouchſafed us his Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments as a ſpecified and ſealed Covenant to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it. Now when a man conveigheth any thing unto us by a ſpecified &amp; Sealed Covenant, we expect it ſure; how much more may we aſſure our ſelves of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of God, ſince he hath given us his written Word and ſeal to confirm it?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Laſtly, Chriſt hath prayed the Father, and he hath ſent the Spirit into our hearts to ſeal every rightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving ſoul unto the day of Redemption, to teſtifie to our ſpirits that we are of God. Tel me now my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, are not all theſe things true? can any conſidering man therefore ſo much as think, that when God hath done ſo much, ſo many waies of our aſſurance, a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoul may not, or ought not to be ſure, that when his body ſhall be diſſolved, his ſoul ſhall have an happie dwelling with God in the heavens?</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 1 Away then, for application, with popiſh doctrine of uncertainty, teaching men to doubt perpetually, and even to the end to diſtruſt our Election and ſalvation;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100971:13"/> It peremptorily affirming that men can have but a meer conjecture, which weighed doth ſcarce amount to a probable opinion. This falſe uncomfortable do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Pontificians, I might iuſtly and ſharply inveigh againſt, but ſuppoſing here are no favourers of Popery I paſſe it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 2 The next inference is matter of complaint, of the ſupine careleſneſſe and groſſe neglect of mens not ſeeking aſſurance of this building not made with hands, being a bleſſed eſtate in Heaven, when theſe dayes of ſin be done. Paſt queſtion a reaſonable ſoul doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire nothing more then to be ſure of the thing it would have, and as ſure it is, that every man pretends to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Heaven, to have his ſoul ſaved when hee departs hence: Yet alas, I grieve to ſee, nothing is ſo little cared for or ſought after, as an aſſurance of Heaven. We would be ſure of health, ſure of meanes, ſure of friends, ſure of preferments, ſure of honour, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the world. To be ſo, wee ſpend our time and ſtrength, uſe all meanes, applie our wits, and are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in nothing which may probably ſecure us: but to be ſure of Heaven, where is the man that acts to the uttermoſt? or doth ſeriouſly endeavour at all? Moſt men make this the leaſt, or no part of their buſineſſe, it comes not into their mindes, ſeldome or never do they think upon it: Others vainely preſume that God will ſure ſave their ſoules: upon falſe or no grounds, they build, yet ſeem to be very confident. Thus ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have preſumed of Heaven, which are now in the depths of Hell. Others deem men can have no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but muſt put it to the mercy of God, and hope well; ſo they do, and thus reſt content. Alaſſe poore ſoules! theſe are very Papiſts in this point, and are like
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100971:14"/> with the reſt of men I ſpeak of, to go to the flames of hell unawares. How can it bee that reaſonable ſouls holding the Proteſtant Religion ſhould ſo fool them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Ah! Damned Satan, it is thy doing, thus to delude poore ſouls, that out of ſlothfulneſſe they might come to hell, rather then take paines to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Heaven. Think ſerioſly my brethren, what folly it is for a Chriſtian to live he knowes not in what ſtate, and when he dies, to go he knows not where; had it not been good for ſuch a man he had never been born? mind this I pray you, and ſuffer this word of reproof to work upon you, that it may not be our caſe in the end.</p>
            <p>What remaines but that we be all ſtirred up and provoked by the power of Gods Word to make ſure of the building, not made with hands. Let not vain preſumptions, blind hopes, and ignorant ſuppoſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile our ſoules. But ſince we evidently ſee, that men may and ought to be aſſured and know, if our earthly houſe be diſſolved, we have a building of God in the Heavens; let us labour after aſſurance: and the better to ſatisfie and prevaile with your ſouls and conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I will acquaint you that there are three kindes of aſſurance.
<list>
                  <item>1 Such as God doth require of all men generally as dutie.</item>
                  <item>2 Such as God doth accept of ſome in mercy.</item>
                  <item>3 Such as God doth vouchſafe to ſome in bounty.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is an aſſurance of evidence: the Lord doth require that all thoſe to whom the word of ſalvation comes, ſhould be ſo well acquainted with it, as to know the promiſes, underſtand aright the properties and characters of thoſe to whom they belong, and be able to evidence to themſelves, that thoſe promſes do
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100971:14"/> belong to them by thoſe properties and characters. That the Spirit by working on thir hearts, doth teſtifie to their ſpirits that they are the Elect of God. To at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this kinde of aſſurance, is the duty of every Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is when a Chriſtian, not ſo well verſed in Gods Book, is not able ſo exactly to applie the promiſes in ſpeciall manner to himſelf, or evidence by any ſuch particular properties and marks. Yet know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in generall the way of Salvation by Chriſt, applied by Faith and repentance to ſinners, doth as it were throw himſelf as a beleeving and penitent ſinner on God, and truſts to be ſaved by the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; and out of this hope, he loves God and Chriſt, deſires and endeavours to forſake all his ſinnes. This I may call a certainty of affiance, which God doth accept of, from many poore ignorant ſoules in mercy.</p>
            <p>The laſt is an aſſurance of obſignation, wherby God doth ſo firmly ſeal the faith of ſome, that they do ſo ſtedfaſtly, &amp; undoubtedly beleeve that Chriſt died for them, as they had ſeen him die on the Croſſe, and he had told them that he did die in particular for them, or as if God from heaven had revealed it by miracle. And whereas it is ſufficient if the two former aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances exceed doubtings, this doth really exclude doubtings. Now this high kind of certainty is uſually given to men after long and fiery trialls, when men have ſtood long, and in an eminent way for Chriſt, as did the Apoſtles, and Martyrs, or when men have been of great ſtanding in piety, and of great integrity in waies of godlines. To ſuch God may, and doubtles doth vouchſafe of his glorious bounty this high kind
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100971:15"/> of aſſurance; but I conceive 'tis not required of all men as a duty. Thus briefly without obſcurity, I have ſhewed you the doctrine of Chriſtian aſſurance: let me ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly entreat and prevail with you, to deſire and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour after this ſweete grace; the excellency, the comfort, the commodities of it are more then ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent motives, if I might illuſtrate them. How good is it at all times, in all conditions of our life, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at our death? I, you will ſay, we do deſire aſſurance, but how ſhall we gain it? I anſwer, we may obtain it,
<list>
                  <item>1. By a cheerfull and ready anſwering the call of God in his Word; when he ſpeakes we muſt hear, ſubmit our wills, yeeld our ſpirits to the power of his ordinances. Such hearing is better then the fat of Rammes, and will by degrees work aſſurance in us.</item>
                  <item>2. By a new and holy converſation: the way to be ſure that we have learned Chriſt, is as touching our former converſation, to put off the old man, which is corrupt according to the deceitfull luſt, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed in the ſpirit of our mindes. If we walk as the prophane how can we hope for aſſurance?</item>
                  <item>3. By expreſſing a true zeal and a religious care for the things of God. S. <hi>Paul</hi> acquaints us, that he which is of God, careth for the things of God. Wen a mans heart is liſtleſſe and unſolicitous of holy things, he may vainely preſume, but cannot warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably aſſure himſelf to belong to the Election of grace.</item>
                  <item>4. By continuall prayer and endeavour to improve in our ſpirituall condition; Add to your faith, vertue; to vertue, knowledge, &amp;c. thus an entrance ſhall be miniſtred abundantly. By a labour to increaſe in ſoul
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100971:15"/> goodneſſe, there will come in ſuch a perfection of love as will caſt out ſlaviſh feares, and ſettle the heart more and more in a ſweet and comfortable aſſurance. Theſe are the directions which I give, and the Lord bleſſe them to you all.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have ended my Text, I might ſtray long to ſpeak of that late grave and worthy Senator, whoſe Funerall we celebrate. My neighbouring abode and ſome acquaintance with him for divers years might furniſh me with plentifull Encomiums of deſerved praiſe; but it's not my guiſe to ſpeak much in this kind; briefly then with good conſcience I may teſtifie him to be a man exemplary in all manner of converſation in his family, in his countrey, in publike, in private af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: Known he was to be a man of great learning, well skilled in the languages of it,<note place="margin">Hebrew, Greek, and Latin.</note> and no ſtranger in its rationall ſyſtems: His many vertues were crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his much zeal for Religion, his great love to zealous, able Miniſters, and good people in the worſt of times: witneſſe, amongſt other things, his Pen in their vindication againſt the gallie inke, which ſprang from a bitter ſpirit,<note place="margin">His Anſwer to the Glaſſe of Schiſmes.</note> and a lying tongue. In a word, he was a true <hi>Mecenas,</hi> a reall Patriot, much loving, and wel-beloved of his Countrey, ſeeking not theirs, but them. The cauſe of piety and Profeſſors was in our parts ſufficiently known to have a friend on the Bench where he ſat. And what was beſt of all, his goodneſſe and vertue did age and increaſe with him: His righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe was not like the morning dew; or, as thoſe who glory to be Patriots for a while, but then like the <hi>ſtellae volantes,</hi> loſe their blazing light, cauſe ſterility, and go out in a ſtenchfull naſtineſſe. Our learned
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100971:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> and religious Brother did ſhine moſt bright in the evening of his dayes: His faithfulneſſe and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, his zeal and affection, his pains and diligence in the great cauſe of God and his holy truth, this Church and Kingdome, deſerveth all commendations, never ending but with his breath. This will juſtly number him among the Worthies of our Engliſh Nation, who have given up themſelves wholly to ſeek the glory of God and the good of the Land. His me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory with theirs ſhal be precious in after ages, maugre all malice: Or, if poſterity ſhould be ſo ungratefull as to forget, yet doubtleſſe their glory will increaſe in a better world. Amongſt whom I ſay, this our bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was not wanting to act his part, even to the end, and ſo hath brought his gray haires with honour to the grave: And now his earthly houſe of this Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle is diſſolved, he hath a building of God, not made with hands, eternall in the Heavens.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
